League of Women Voters of Cambridge. Records, 1916-1957: A Finding Aid
Records, 1916-ca.1976
MC 264
Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute
League of Women Voters of Cambridge
1 file box, 3 reels of microfilm (M-103)
Minutes, reports, correspondence, etc., of the League of Women Voters of Cambridge (Mass.), which advocated for informed, active participation of citizens in government.
Accession numbers: 59-27, and parts of 1240, and 84-M168
The records of the League of Women Voters of Cambridge were given to the Schlesinger Library by the League, and by Louise (Fletcher) Chase, a past president of the League, beginning in March 1959. The scrapbooks and clippings (1v -15) were prepared for microfilming by Catherine Cooper in March 1986.
HISTORY
The Cambridge Political Equality Association was organized in February 1896 by women who believed "that the exercise of the suffrage on the part of the women citizens is not only just but will promote a better civic life, the true development of the home, and the welfare of the family...." Association records for the years 1896 to 1916 are in: the Schlesinger Library's Woman's Rights Collection (folders 1070-1081af, volumes 106-110); the Grace A. Johnson papers in the Woman's Rights Collection (Jo-161--Jo-164); and in the Maud Wood Park papers in the Woman's Rights Collection (Pa-155). In 1916 the CPEA was reorganized as the Third Middlesex Representative District Organization of the Massachusetts Woman Suffrage Association. In 1920 it became the League of Women Voters of Cambridge.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The file box contains minutes: of regular meetings (1916-1920, 1923-1928), of annual meetings (1916-1920, 1923-1943, 1945-1957), and of the executive committee (1920-1930). Eight oversized scrapbooks and seven folders of clippings were microfilmed (M-103) and returned to the League. Unprocessed addenda include additional minutes, reports, correspondence, and other papers.
The eight scrapbooks document the activities of the League from its inception in 1920 until 1964. The contents of the scrapbooks were arranged chronologically and consist of programs and other printed material, invitations, correspondence, and clippings about the League and about the community issues with which the League concerned itself.
Because of the chronological arrangement of the scrapbooks and the variety of materials collected in them, the inventory does not describe in detail the contents of each volume. The index that follows the inventory provides the volume and page number of references to important women.
MICROFILM OF SCRAPBOOKS AND CLIPPINGS
The eight scrapbooks and seven folders of clippings were microfilmed with the support of the Friends of the Schlesinger Library. The scrapbooks, their contents, and the loose clippings were fragile and could not be handled without damage. Some or all of the following conditions apply to each volume.
1. Glue or tape has caused discoloration, which affects the legibility of some items.
2. In some instances, glue or tape has dried and clippings or other items are loose. Loose items were filmed where they were found, when possible; otherwise, they were filmed immediately after that page. Whenever possible, these items were filmed in the order in which they are to be read. Where necessary to avoid confusion, items under those being filmed were masked before filming.
3. Many scrapbook pages contain items that overlap, were folded in order to fit on the page, or have multiple pages. These scrapbook pages were filmed as they first appeared and then as many more times as necessary.
4. In general, multiple-paged items by or about the League of Women Voters of Cambridge were filmed in their entirety. An exception to this rule was made in the case of minutes of Board and Annual Meetings, and issues of League Items, the League newsletter, which are duplicated in the unprocessed part of the collection. In the case of these materials, only those single items which are not duplicated elsewhere were filmed in their entirety.
5. In the case of multiple-paged items not having primarily to do with the LWVC, only covers or first pages and any pages concerning the LWVC were filmed. Publications by or about the League of Women Voters of Massachusetts may be found in the LWVM collection in the Schlesinger Library; the Library of Congress is the official repository for the records of the League of Women Voters of the U.S.
6. Because of the brittle state of many clippings, some text has been lost. This has happened in particular at the edges of pages, and where one clipping was glued over another and was too fragile to be folded back.
7. Page numbers in square brackets were added by the processor to aid the microfilmer, the proofreader, and the researcher; blank pages were not numbered.
8. When possible, correspondence, pamphlets, brochures, programs, invitations, and newsletters were removed from the scrapbooks after microfilming; they have been integrated with the unprocessed portion of the collection.
REEL GUIDE
When requesting microfilmed material, please use the microfilm number, M-103, and the reel number:
Reel 1: 1vo-5vo
Reel 2: 6vo-7vo
Reel 3: 8vo-15
CONTAINER LIST
Box 1: 1vo-22v
Reel M-103
INVENTORY
- Scrapbooks and clippings., 1vo-15:
  AVAILABLE ON MICROFILM (M-103).
  - Scrapbooks: clippings, correspondence, minutes, programs, newsletters, invitations, 1vo-8vo:
    - Jan. 1921 - April 1929, 1vo.
    - May 1929 - Dec. 1931, 2vo.
    - Jan. 1932 - April 1934, 3vo.
    - April 1934 - Aug. 1936, 4vo.
    - Aug. 1936 - Nov. 1939, 5vo.
    - Nov. 1939 - Feb. 1949, 6vo.
    - Feb. 1949 - Feb. 1959, 7vo.
    - Feb. 1959 - Oct. 1964, 8vo.
  - Clippings, 9-15:
    - Voter's Service Candidate Profiles, 192?-197?, 9.
    - School of Politics, 1928, 10.
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1931-1945, 11.
    - Schools, 1945: scrapbook leaves, 12.
    - Schools, 1957, 13.
    - Zoning, 1961-1962, 14.
    - Clippings, 1972-1974, 15.
- Minutes, 16v-22v:
  - Annual, open, and business meetings of the CPEA and the Third Middlesex Representative District Organization of the MWSA, October 16, 1916 - December 1, 1920. Also, LWVC meetings, May 1924 (annual meeting) - February 10, 1925., 16v.
  - Open meetings, 1923-1928; annual meetings, 1923-1941., 17v.
  - Loose papers removed from 17v, 18.
  - Annual meetings, 1942-1943, 1945-1957, 19v.
  - Loose papers removed from 19v, 20.
  - Executive committee (also called executive board), December 9, 1920 - February 3, 1925, 21v.
  - Executive committee (also called executive board), February 16, 1925 - February 12, 1930, 22v.
Additional catalog entries
Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950; Cambridge Political Equality Association; League of Women Voters of Massachusetts; League of Women Voters of the United States; Massachusetts Woman Suffrage Association. Third Middlesex Representative District Organization; Andrews, Fannie Fern (Phillips), 1867-1950; Associations, institutions, etc.; Breshkovsky, Catherine, 1844-1934; Bronner, Augusta Fox, 1881-1966; Brown, Dorothy (Kirchwey), 1888-1981; Cambridge (Mass.)--Clubs; Cambridge (Mass.)--Politics and government; Cambridge (Mass.)--Study and teaching; Cambridge (Mass.)--Voting registers; Cambridge (Mass.)--Zoning maps; Cannon, Ida Maud, 1877-1960; Civics--Massachusetts--Cambridge; Cronkhite, Bernice Veazey (Brown), 1893-1983; Eliot, Martha May, 1891-1978; Hamilton, Alice, 1869-1970; Harvard Scrubwomen; Hodder, Jessie (Donaldson), 1867-1931; Howe, Helen, 1905-1975; Irwin, Inez (Haynes), 1873-1970; Luscomb, Florence Hope, 1887-1985; Park, Maud (Wood), 1871-1955; Politics, Practical--Massachusetts--Cambridge; Sayre, Jessie (Wilson), 1887-1933; Schlesinger, Elizabeth (Bancroft), 1887-1977; School boards; Societies; Strong, Anna Louise, 1885-1970; Suffrage--Massachusetts; Van Waters, Miriam, 1887-1974; Voting; Wambaugh, Sarah, 1882-1956
NAME INDEX
The following index gives the volume and page numbers of references to notable women in the microfilmed scrapbooks (1vo-8vo). Due to poor contrast, however, page numbers are only infrequently legible (1vo-7vo).
Andrews, Fannie Fern (Phillips) 3:123
Blackwell, Alice Stone 2:36, 2:39, 4:4, 4:23, 4:70, 4:71, 4:142, 5:1, 6:94, 6:103, 8:80
Breshkovsky, Catherine 4:23
Bronner, Augusta Fox 2:3
Brown, Dorothy (Kirchwey) 3:126
Cannon, Ida Maud 5:12, 5:14, 5:15
Cronkhite, Bernice Veazey (Brown) 1:9, 1:25, 2:85, 6:7, 6:42
Eliot, Martha May 8:13, 8:40
Hamilton, Alice 3:109, 3:113, 3:115
Harvard Scrubwomen 2:24
Hodder, Jessie (Donaldson) 1:12
Howe, Helen 1:47, 1:48, 5:27, 5:34
Irwin, Inez (Haynes) 6:91
Luscomb, Florence Hope 1:17, 1:24, 2:34
Park, Maud (Wood) 6:91
Sayre, Jessie (Wilson) 1:13, 1:69, 2:5, 2:20, 2:21, 2:22, 2:39, 3:69, 4:68
Schlesinger, Elizabeth (Bancroft) 2:85, 2:121, 2:125, 2:126, 2:127, 2:129, 2:130, 2:131, 3:12, 3:41, 3:88, 3:89, 4:32
Strong, Anna Louise 4:110, 4:112, 4:113
Van Waters, Miriam 3:125, 3:129, 4:68, 5:111, 5:113, 6:141
Wambaugh, Sarah 1:6, 1:12, 1:28, 1:65, 1:66, 2:3, 2:20, 2:21, 2:22, 2:92, 2:93, 3:18, 3:97, 3:99, 3:142, 4:4, 4:40, 4:41, 4:49, 4:51, 4:52, 4:53, 4:55, 4:56, 4:57, 4:77, 4:78, 4:99, 4:102, 4:123, 5:16, 6:7